Stanford R. Inman Papers VHP2004/4
CCSU Veterans History Project
Stanford R. Inman Papers
Bulk, 1943-1945
1943 - 1945, 1988, 1990,2004
VHP2004/4
CCSU Veterans History Project
45.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
Inman, Stanford R., (Stanford Ralph)
Biographical Note
Stanford Inman, a native of Foxboro, Massachusetts enlisted in the United States Marine Corps in 1943 and served until 1946. During his enlistment Sergeant Inman was trained as a B-25 Aviation Mechanic-Turret Gunner and assigned to Marine Bomber Squadron 613 (VMB-613). The squadron trained at Quantico, in Oklahoma, Arkansas and Miramar Naval Base in San Diego before deployment to Hawaii and Kwajalein where Stanford and the squadron saw combat on Pohnpei Island, one of the four states within the Federated States of Micronesia.
Scope Note
This collection details Stanford Inman’s training as well as his flight and combat experiences during World War II. An oral history interview was conducted on November 5, 2004 at Stanford’s home by Eileen Hurst, Associate Director of the Center for Public Policy and Social Research. Along with Stanford’s oral history interview the collection contains print and digitized copies of personal and military manuscripts, and photographs. This collection provides evidence of the military take over and control of Kwajalein Atoll by the United States during World War II as it follows the training, deployment, and convoy patrols performed by Marine Bombing Squadron 613.
Arrangement Note
This collection is arranged based on content and material type into series:
Series I, Personal papers
Series II, Military documents
Series III, Multi-media
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Online Access
An Online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
United States. Marine Corps. Bombing Squadron 613.; United States. Marine Corps.; Kwajalein Island (Marshall Islands); Marine Corps Air Station Cherry Point (N.C.); Mitchell bomber; Pohnpei Island (Micronesia); World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945--Aerial operations, American.
- Series I: Personal Papers, 1945, 2004
  - U.S. Marine Bombing Squadron 613 signature list, 1945; 2004/4.I.1
    Related Archival Materials note
    List of signatures which correspond to a group photograph taken of Marine Bomber Squadron 613’s Mechanic Gunners (item 2004/4.IIIa.39)
  - Synopsis of oral history interview with Stanford R. Inman, 1945; 2004/4.I.2
  - Certificate of Appreciation, undate; 2004/4.I.3
- Series II: Military Documents, 1988 - 1990
  - Aerial map of military compound on Kwajalein Atoll., undate; 2004/4.II.1
  - Message from commandant, General A.M. Gray during Marine Bomber Squadron 613 reunion, June 21, 1988; 2004/4.II.2
  - Two page contact list consisting of Marine Bombing Squadron 613 members, undate; 2004/4.II.3
- Series III: Multi-Media
  - Subseries A: Still Images, 1943 - 1945
    - Military portrait of Stanford Inman in dress blues, Feb. 1943; 2004/4.IIIa.1
    - Stanford Inman (l) and George Hock (r) posing with rifles, Parris Island, South Carolina, 1943; 2004/4.IIIa.2
    - Ray Hawco (l) and Stanford Inman (r) on the rifle range in a seated position, Parris Island, S.C., 1943; 2004/4.IIIa.3
    - George Hock (l) and Stanford Inman (r) on the rifle range in a prone position, Parris Island, S.C., 1943; 2004/4.IIIa.4
    - Ray Hawco (l), George Hock (c) and Stanford Inman (r) on the rifle range in a kneeling position, Parris Island, S.C., 1943; 2004/4.IIIa.5
    - Aiming at a target on the rifle range is Ray Hawco (l), George Hock (c) and Stanford Inman (r), Parris Island, S.C., 1943; 2004/4.IIIa.6
    - View of Diamond Head on the way to Kwajalein, Oahu, Hawaii, undate; 2004/4.IIIa.7
    - Aerial view of an Aircraft Carrier on its’ way to Kwajalein, Marshall Islands, 1944; 2004/4.IIIa.8
    - SB2C airplane, Roi Namur, 1944; 2004/4.IIIa.9
    - Majuro Tower, Island in the Marshall Islands, 1944-1945; 2004/4.IIIa.10
    - Aerial view of Convoy off Enewetak, Marshall Islands, 1944; 2004/4.IIIa.11
    - U.S. barracks, Enewetak, Marshall Islands, 1944; 2004/4.IIIa.12
    - Aerial view of U.S. troop barracks (1 of 3), Kwajalein, Marshall Islands, 1944 - 1945; 2004/4.IIIa.13
    - Aerial view of U.S. troop barracks (2 of 3), Kwajalein, Marshall Islands, 1944 - 1945; 2004/4.IIIa.14
    - Aerial view of U.S. troop barracks (3 of 3), Kwajalein, Marshall Islands, 1944 - 1945; 2004/4.IIIa.15
    - C-64 airplane, Kwajalein, Marshall Islands, 1944 - 1945; 2004/4.IIIa.16
    - B-29 bomber, Kwajalein, Marshall Islands, 1944 - 1945; 2004/4.IIIa.17
    - Military personnel enjoying a game of basketball, Kwajalein, Marshall Islands, 1944 - 1945; 2004/4.IIIa.18
    - Eddie Kerig (l) and Dick Riggle (r) leaning on a military vehicle wearing holstered side arms, Kwajalein, Marshall Islands, 1944 - 1945; 2004/4.IIIa.19
    - Stanford Inman (l), Warren Ritter (c) and Charles Cannato (r), Kwajalein, Marshall Islands, 1944 - 1945; 2004/4.IIIa.20
    - In hats and side arms from left to right Eddie Kreig, Thomas “Bo” Bohannon, Stanford Inman and Dick Riggle, Kwajalein, Marshall Islands, 1944 - 1945; 2004/4.IIIa.21
    - Posing in front of a plank building standing left to right in the back row is Warren Ritter, Thomas Bohannon and Bob Dillon. In the front row kneeling left to right are Stanford Inman and William Wright, Kwajalein, Marshall Islands, 1944 - 1945; 2004/4.IIIa.22
    - Friendly group of squadron members from left to right Warren Ritter, Lou Brosius and William Wright Kwajalein, Marshall Islands, 1944 - 1945; 2004/4.IIIa.23
    - In jumpsuits from left to right Charles Cannato, Bob Dillon and Warren Ritter, Kwajalein, Marshall Islands, 1944 - 1945; 2004/4.IIIa.24
    - Mechanic Air Crewmen VMB 613. Stanford Inman is kneeling on the far right of the middle row, Kwajalein, Marshall Islands, 1944 - 1945; 2004/4.IIIa.25
    - Stanford Inman (foreground) seen leaving the showers, Kwajalein, Marshall Islands, 1944 - 1945; 2004/4.IIIa.26
    - Posing in swimsuits from left to right, Allan Dover, Lou Brosius and Stanford Inman, Kwajalein, Marshall Islands, 1944 - 1945; 2004/4.IIIa.27
    - Marine Bomber Squadron flight crew. Back row standing left to right, Mike Brennan (Sergeant Navigator), Dan Hazelnus (Co-pilot), Wayne Youngren (Pilot), Donald Clay (Radio gunner). Front row kneeling left to right, Wayne Mathews (Ordnance), John “Chico” Duarte (Radio) and Stanford Inman (Mechanic gunner), Kwajalein, Marshall Islands, 1944 - 1945; 2004/4.IIIa.28
    - Members of Marine Bomber Squadron 613 posing on the beach. Stanford Inman, back row center, Kwajalein, Marshall Islands, 1944 - 1945; 2004/4.IIIa.29
    - Marine Bomber Squadron 613 members enjoying the beach. Stanford Inman, seated far right, Kwajalein, Marshall Islands, 1944 - 1945; 2004/4.IIIa.30
    - Posing on the beach with the Majuro Tower in the background. Back row standing, Lou Brosius, Bob Dillon and Tony Blaso. Front row kneeling, Warren Ritter and Stanford Inman, Kwajalein, Marshall Islands, 1944 - 1945; 2004/4.IIIa.31
    - Cast of Arsenic & Old Lace with members of Marine Bomber Squadron 613. Squadron members from left to right Alan Dover, Lou Brosius and John Gavin, Kwajalein, Marshall Islands, 1945; 2004/4.IIIa.32
    - Cast of Arsenic & Old Lace, Kwajalein, Marshall Islands, 1945; 2004/4.IIIa.33
    - Sergeant John J. Gavin from Troy, New York posing in a foxhole, Bennett Island, Jan 17, 1945; 2004/4.IIIa.34
    - Lou Brosius posing with his rifle on R & R, Bascomb Island, 1945; 2004/4.IIIa.35
    - Troops aboard ship as they depart for home (U.S.), Kwajalein, Marshall Islands, 1945; 2004/4.IIIa.36
    - View of troops in military vehicle arriving at ship for transport to the United States, Kwajalein, Marshall Islands, 1945; 2004/4.IIIa.37
    - Military vessel on route to the United States, Kwajalein, Marshall Islands, 1945; 2004/4.IIIa.38
    - Mechanic gunners. Stanford Inman back row, standing, third from left, Kwajalein, Marshall Islands, 1945; 2004/4.IIIa.39
  - Subseries B: Moving Images, 2004
    - Oral history interview with Stanford R. Inman, Nov. 5, 2004; 2004/4.IIIb.1 (Disk DVD VHP2004/4, Box VHP Interview 1)
      Existence and Location of Copies note
      Interview video also available in video DVD dics, and
      Online Streaming Video